Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1319
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 6. Manuscripts, 1896-1981; 18 boxes
  - 6E. Monographs, 1896-1980; 5 boxes
    - Brothers Under the Skin--Forward and introduction, 1963-1964; 7 items. (Box 82, Folder 3)
      Typewritten manuscripts of the forward and introduction for the 1964 edition.
    - California: the Great Exception, 1967-1973; 11 items. (Box 82, Folder 4)
      Correspondence with publishers Hill and Wang, reprint requests, and letters from the Greenwood Press.
    - Factories in the Field--Correspondence (1 of 5), 1938; 8 items. (Box 82, Folder 5)
      Two letters from publishers rejecting the manuscript. Also contains undated correspondence, and (mostly positive) reviews.
    - Factories in the Field--Correspondence (2 of 5), 1939 June-August; ca. 40 items. (Box 82, Folder 6)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence from critics, fans, and publishers, and copies of McWilliams's replies. Includes a manuscript draft of Louis Adamic's review of Factories.
    - Factories in the Field--Correspondence (3 of 5), 1939 September-December; ca. 40 items. (Box 82, Folder 7)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence from critics, fans, and publishers, and copies of McWilliams's replies. Includes an acknowledgement from the White House that First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt has read the book.
    - Factories in the Field--Correspondence (4 of 5), 1940-1941; 31 items. (Box 82, Folder 8)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence from critics, fans, and publishers, and copies of McWilliams's replies. Includes an invitation to speak before the New York Committee to Aid Agricultural Workers.
    - Factories in the Field--Correspondence (5 of 5), 1951-1972; 16 items. (Box 82, Folder 9)
      General letters regarding the re-issue of the text, and copies of McWilliams's replies.
    - Factories in the Field--Notes and outline, ca. 1950-1951, 1967; 7 items. (Box 82, Folder 10)
      Typewritten notes and an outline manuscript.
    - Factories in the Field--Notes, reviews and clippings, 1939-1941, 1968-1972; ca. 40 items. (Box 82, Folder 11)
      Handwritten and typed notes, clippings of reviews of the text, and clippings that mention Factories or touch on farm labor.
    - Factories in the Field--Requests for permission to quote, 1951, 1962-1974; 23 items. (Box 82, Folder 12)
    - Ill Fares the Land--Correspondence (1 of 3), 1941-1942; 33 items. (Box 83, Folder 1)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence from critics, fans, and publishers, and copies of McWilliams's replies.
    - Ill Fares the Land--Correspondence (2 of 3), 1951-1953, 1965-1967; 13 items. (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - Ill Fares the Land--Correspondence (3 of 3), 1970-1976; 21 items. (Box 83, Folder 3)
      Publisher correspondence.
    - Ill Fares the Land--Reprint. "The Joads at Home.", undated; 1 item. (Box 83, Folder 4)
    - Ill Fares the Land--Royalty statements and agreements, 1967-1979; 26 items. (Box 83, Folder 5)
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Correspondence regarding Adamic (1 of 2), 1951-1952; 36 items. (Box 83, Folder 6)
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Correspondence regarding Adamic (2 of 2), 1966-1980; 33 items. (Box 83, Folder 7)
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Correspondence with Adamic, 1931-1939, 1949-1951; 24 items. (Box 83, Folder 8)
      Letters between Adamic and McWilliams.
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Manuscript, 1934-1935; 2 items. (Box 83, Folder 9)
      69 pages of typewritten manuscript; publisher's prospectus.
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Miscellaneous research file, 1930-1951, 1977-1978; 33 items. (Box 83, Folder 10)
      Handwritten and typewritten notes, 3 black and white photographs of Adamic, 4 manuscripts by Adamic (chapters XII-XV, ca. 1949), clippings, and assorted printed materials.
    - Louis Adamic and Shadow-America--Printed materials, 1929-1935, 1949-1951, 1973-1979; ca. 50 items. (Box 83, Folder 11)
      Published writings, either by Adamic or about him, including a Nation article by McWilliams, reviews, and newspaper clippings regarding Adamic's death.
    - A Mask for Privilege--Clippings and reviews, 1948; ca. 20 items. (Box 83, Folder 12)
      Includes the critique from the Anti-Defamation League and McWilliams's response.
    - A Mask for Privilege--Miscellaneous research file, 1978; 5 items. (Box 83, Folder 13)
      Correspondence, clippings, and extensive typed notes and quotations from published works.
    - The Mexicans in America, 1966-1970; 55 items. (Box 83, Folder 14)
      Typewritten manuscript for The Mexicans in America: A Students' Guide to Localized History. Includes editor and publisher correspondence, royally statements, contracts, and a bibliography.
    - North from Mexico--Assorted printed materials, 1949, 1959, 1966-1979; 38 items. (Box 84, Folder 1)
      Typewritten notes, a press release, a manuscript (Borderland by Robert Joseph and Edward Cahn), financial statements, reviews, copy of El Grito with letter, leaflets, newsletters, catalogs, and clippings.
    - North from Mexico--Bibliography, undated; 1 item. (Box 84, Folder 2)
      Contains 92 pages of typed notes and quotations from published works.
    - North from Mexico--Correspondence (1 of 4), 1949-1961; 25 items. (Box 84, Folder 3)
    - North from Mexico--Correspondence (2 of 4), 1966-1968; 36 items. (Box 84, Folder 4)
    - North from Mexico--Correspondence (3 of 4), 1969; 26 items. (Box 84, Folder 5)
    - North from Mexico--Correspondence (4 of 4), 1970; 39 items. (Box 84, Folder 6)
    - North from Mexico--Film adaptation, 1970-1972, 1976; 15 items. (Box 84, Folder 7)
      Correspondence, promotional materials, script treatment, newsletter, and bibliography.
    - North from Mexico--General subject file, 1967-1972,1979-1980; 24 items. (Box 84, Folder 8)
      Articles and clippings do not discuss book, but touch on its subjects. Also contains a letter, and a paper entitled "The land question in New Mexico" (author unknown).
    - North from Mexico--Manuscript. "Introduction", 1968 January 2; 4 items. (Box 84, Folder 9)
      Typewritten manuscripts for the 1968 introduction.
    - North from Mexico--Manuscript. "The Mexicans in America", undated; 1 item. (Box 84, Folder 10)
    - North from Mexico--Manuscript. "Once a well-kept secret", 1973; 2 items. (Box 84, Folder 11)
      Typewritten manuscript, and a published reprint.
    - North from Mexico--Manuscript. Untitled fragment, undated; 1 item. (Box 84, Folder 12)
    - North from Mexico--Notebook, undated; 1 item. (Box 84, Folder 13)
      Handwritten notes and quotations from published works.
    - North from Mexico--Permission requests and correspondence, 1969-1980; 26 items. (Box 84, Folder 14)
    - North from Mexico--Siglo Veintiuno Editores, 1968-1979; 50 items. (Box 84, Folder 15)
      Correspondence, royalty statements, and clippings
    - Prejudice--Articles, clippings, and reviews, 1944-1945, 1965-1966, 1970; 10 items. (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Prejudice--Correspondence (1 of 2), 1951-1952, 1966-1972; 40 items. (Box 85, Folder 2)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence, mostly regarding permission to quote requests, and copies of McWilliams's replies.
    - Prejudice--Correspondence (2 of 2), 1974-1978; 28 items. (Box 85, Folder 3)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence, mostly regarding permission to quote requests, and copies of McWilliams's replies. Includes a draft of a paper by Stuart L. Deutsch entitled, "The California legal profession and Japanese exclusion."
    - [Religion], 1943-1949; 19 items. (Box 85, Folder 4)
      Typewritten outlines, chapters, and drafts for an untitled book on religion. Includes a letter from Maxim Lieber, author's agent.
    - Southern California Country--Correspondence (1 of 2), 1943-1970; 51 items. (Box 85, Folder 5)
      Handwritten and typewritten correspondence from critics, fans, and publishers, and copies of McWilliams's replies. Includes lecture invitations.
    - Southern California Country--Correspondence (2 of 2), 1971-1979; 73 items. (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - Southern California Country--Introduction, 1972; 1 item. (Box 85, Folder 7)
      Typewritten manuscript for the 1973 version.
    - Southern California Country--Miscellaneous, 1944-1951, 1968-1979; 45 items. (Box 85, Folder 8)
      Chronology, reviews, publisher catalogs, royalty statements, signed agreements, affidavit regarding Katherine Tingley, clippings, and assorted printed materials.
    - The Education of Carey McWilliams--Lecture draft. "McCarthyism and American policy, ca. 1960; 9 items. (Box 85, Folder 9)
      Typewritten outlines, notes, and letters related to The Education of Carey McWilliams, the Cold War and McCarthyism.
    - The Education of Carey McWilliams--Manuscript. "Introduction", 1974-1977; 2 items. (Box 85, Folder 10)
      Typewritten manuscript of the 1974 introduction and photocopy of the published version.
    - The Education of Carey McWilliams--Manuscript. "The Education of Carey McWilliams: an interim report", ca. 1960; 4 items. (Box 85, Folder 11)
      Typewritten manuscripts and an outline.
    - The Education of Carey McWilliams--Miscellaneous, 1923, 1974; 12 items. (Box 85, Folder 12)
      Correspondence, signed contract, and printed material.
- 7. The Nation, 1894-1980; 3 boxes
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, general subject files, and assorted printed materials that were originally labeled by McWilliams as files specifically relating to The Nation. Other materials related to The Nation are found throughout the collection, especially in the correspondence and research files (Subseries 2A, 2B, 2C), and in the manuscript files (Subseries 6A, 6B, 6C). Arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1957; 24 items. (Box 86, Folder 1)
    With Freda Kirchwey, C. Wright Mills, Helen Alfred, and others. Also includes memoranda (one listing articles appearing in The Nation that were not "soft on communism"), 3 letters from John F. Kennedy, a letter from William Wyler, and a statement in Spanish from Diego Rivera giving The Nation permission to use his mural, "Gloriosa Victoria."
  - Correspondence, 1958; 37 items. (Box 86, Folder 2)
    With B. J. Widick, Arnold H. Maremont, and others. Also includes memoranda and clippings.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1961; 14 items. (Box 86, Folder 3)
    With Arnold H. Maremont. Also includes memoranda, a clipping, a letter from Saul Bass, and a letter from George Kirstein concerning limited partners.
  - Correspondence, 1962; 25 items. (Box 86, Folder 4)
    With William H. Fitzpatrick, Jacques Calmy, Everett Mendelsohn, and Cyril J. Bath. Also includes letters, memoranda, and clippings.
  - Correspondence, 1963; 16 items. (Box 86, Folder 5)
    Also includes memoranda and clippings.
  - Correspondence, 1965-1967; 14 items. (Box 86, Folder 6)
    With Karl M. Ruppenthal. Also contains letters (including one to Ralph Ingersoll in which McWilliams explains The Nation's "specialness"), and memoranda (including one on editorial policy, and 2 to James Storrow).
  - Correspondence, 1968; 30 items. (Box 86, Folder 7)
    With James Storrow, Vic Bernstein, Willie D. Jacobs, and David B. Lord. Also contains memoranda, and letters (including recommendations from Lawrence Clark Powell and John J. Clopine).
  - Correspondence, 1969-1973; 13 items. (Box 86, Folder 8)
    With George Salzman, and Rita Lawrence. Also includes letters, and McWilliams's memorandum on "night thoughts" about The Nation (9 pgs.).
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976; 29 items. (Box 86, Folder 9)
    With Peter Miller, James Storrow, Blair Clark, James Dembin, Richard D. Hongisto, and Kingsley Widmer. Also includes letters and memoranda.
  - Correspondence, 1977-1980; 25 items. (Box 86, Folder 10)
    With Hamilton Fish, James and Linda Storrow, and between Milton Viorst and Storrow. Also includes letters (1 from Blair Clark to Cesar Chavez), and a statement of editorial content by Viorst.
  - Correspondence--Resignation, 1975 September; 49 items. (Box 86, Folder 11)
    Includes letters from Jake Zeitlin, and Studs Terkel.
  - Correspondence--Resignation, 1975 October; 39 items. (Box 86, Folder 12)
    Includes letters from Stanley Mosk, Lillie Shultz, and Bernard Nossiter.
  - Correspondence--Resignation, 1975 November; 11 items. (Box 86, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence--Resignation, 1975 December; 21 items. (Box 86, Folder 14)
    Includes letters from Theodore Roszak, and James M. Cain.
  - Correspondence--Resignation, 1976; 12 items. (Box 86, Folder 15)
  - Journals of Opinion, 1956-1971; 38 items. (Box 87, Folder 1)
    Correspondence with Charles Frankel concerning a possible international conference to be sponsored by The Nation for the editors of critical opinion journals. Also includes 2 letters, a typewritten outline, a press release, 3 leaflets (2 concerning The Nation's 100th birthday and the other a Nation anthology), articles (3 by McWilliams: "The Nation and the Magazine of Opinion," "Who Says So?" and "One Hundred Years of The Nation"), and clippings mostly referring to The Nation.
  - The Kirchwey Years, 1941-1977; 47 items. (Box 87, Folder 2)
    Letters (primarily concerning the federal indictments of Harvey Matusow, R. Lawrence Siegel, Hadassah R. Shapiro, and Martin Solow), a memo from McWilliams to M.R. Werner about censorship in the publishing industry, handwritten and typed notes, an annotated manuscript draft fragment, clippings, and assorted printed materials concerning a 1952 dinner forum of The Nation Associates on Arab-Israel Peace (including an untitled manuscript). Also contains McWilliams's articles: "Goldwaterism: The New Ideology," "High Noon in the Cow Palace," "The Last Optimist," and "The Freda Kirchwey I Knew." This material was possibly compiled for a chapter in The Education of Carey McWilliams.
  - The Kirstein Years (1 of 3), 1950-1977; 74 items. (Box 87, Folder 3)
    Correspondence (with Samuel Shapiro and Norman Birnbaum, and Mrs. Walter H. Hatch), letters, a list of labor articles, a pamphlet, leaflets, extensive handwritten and typed notes, and articles. Includes 2 letters and a typewritten poem from John Ciardi. This material was possibly compiled for a chapter in The Education of Carey McWilliams.
  - The Kirstein Years (2 of 3), 1964-1976; 11 items. (Box 87, Folder 4)
    2 pamphlets ("Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam" and "Hughes for Senate"), a paper by Dr. Frederick Schuman entitled, "The Neuroses of The Nations," and newspaper clippings. This material was possibly compiled for a chapter in The Education of Carey McWilliams.
  - The Kirstein Years (3 of 3), 1952-1978; 31 items. (Box 87, Folder 5)
    A press release, and clippings. Includes a McWilliams's review of a book on the Rosenbergs. This material was possibly compiled for a chapter in The Education of Carey McWilliams.
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (1 of 6), 1932-1935; 8 items. (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (2 of 6), 1941-1948; 48 items. (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (3 of 6), 1949-1951; 33 items. (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (4 of 6), 1962-1968; 4 items. (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (5 of 6), 1973-1977; 34 items. (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - McWilliams's writings, clippings (6 of 6), 1978-1980; 41 items. (Box 87, Folder 11)
    Includes the Second Thoughts column.
  - The Nation Associates' Conference on The Challenge of the Post-War World to the Liberal Movement, 1946 September-October; 4 items. (Box 87, Folder 12)
    An invitation to the dinner forum, and clippings.
  - The Nation Institute Conference on American Foreign Policy, 1967 January-March; 30 items. (Box 88, Folder 1)
    Correspondence (with Rita Lawrence, George McGovern, Eliot Macy, and Nancy Reeves), letters of thanks from McWilliams to those who participated in the conference, a copy of the speech given by Martin Luther King, Jr., a typewritten manuscript of Malcolm W. Browne's remarks, as well as a copy of Eugene J. McCarthy's remarks entitled, "Moral Aspects of the War in Vietnam." Also includes McWilliams's typewritten outline for the preliminary meeting and a copy of his address "The New Constituencies." This conference took place on February 25, 1967. (See also box 67, folder 18)
  - The Nation Report, 1958, 1965-1966; 2 items. (Box 88, Folder 2)
    The report is for the period from August 1, 1965 to August 1 1966. Also includes a 1958 memorandum from McWilliams.
  - Parochial Schools and Public Leadership, 1960-1960; 4 items. (Box 88, Folder 3)
    An address by Myron Lieberman, which mentions The Nation, delivered to the Diocesan Superintendents Section of the National Catholic Education Association. Also contains correspondence with George Kirstein and a letter to Lieberman.
  - Prospectus, 1977 April; 1 item. (Box 88, Folder 4)
    By Hamilton Fish, concerning his goals for The Nation.
  - Publicity (1 of 2), 1894, 1950-1978; 25 items. (Box 88, Folder 5)
    Press releases, WCBS-TV program transcripts, leaflets, and articles about or mentioning The Nation. Includes the photocopy of a letter from Theodore Roosevelt, and 2 articles by McWilliams: "100 Years of The Nation" and "A Frank Appraisal of the Press."
  - Publicity (2 of 2), 1959-1980; 26 items. (Box 88, Folder 6)
    Clippings, about or mentioning The Nation.
  - Special Issues (1 of 2), 1946, 1951-1953, 1956, 1976; 9 items. (Box 88, Folder 7)
    Copies of The Nation, reprints, a photocopy, and a clipping. Includes articles by McWilliams: "The Education of Carey McWilliams and Civil Rights," "Enforce the Constitution," and "Triumph of Moderation."
  - Special Issues (2 of 2), 1959-1966; 6 items. (Box 88, Folder 8)
    Copies of The Nation and a clipping.
  - Typewritten notes and lists, 1955-1974; 28 items. (Box 88, Folder 9)
    Lists of limited partners, contacts, awards, pieces on conservation, references to Red China, and signed articles dealing with Vietnam. Also includes quotations, bibliographies, a memo on editorial policy, and McWilliams's European work schedules.
  - Writings, clippings (1 of 2), 1946-1950; ca. 70 items. (Box 88, Folder 10)
  - Writings, clippings (2 of 2), 1948, 1957-1979; 41 items. (Box 88, Folder 11)
- 8. Printed materials, 1925-1980; 1 box
  This series primarily consists of clippings of articles, reviews and reprints written by McWilliams that appeared in a variety of publications. Some pamphlets are included. Additional published writings by McWilliams may be found in the scrapbooks (Subseries 1D), his files on people (Subseries 2A), his general subject files (Subseries 2B), and The Nation files (Series 7). Arranged in chronological order, with undated materials at the beginning of the series.
  - Clippings from assorted publications, undated; 15 items. (Box 89, Folder 1)
    Includes Haldeman-Julius Monthly and The Antioch Review.
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1925-1929; 11 items. (Box 89, Folder 2)
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1930-1938; 25 items. (Box 89, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of Panorama, the Bar Bulletin, and 2 pamphlets: "It Can Happen Here: Active Anti-Semitism in Los Angeles" and "The Kramer Bill and Charles Kramer."
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1931-1937; ca. 20 items. (Box 89, Folder 4)
    Includes News of the World.
  - Clippings of the Westways columns "California Curiosa" and "Tides West", 1933-1939; ca. 70 items. (Box 89, Folder 5)
    Includes 1 letter from 1976 that mentions a possible book compilation.
  - Clippings from Pacific Weekly, 1935-1937; 9 items. (Box 89, Folder 6)
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1940-1948; 18 items. (Box 89, Folder 7)
    Includes 1 letter, 2 newsletters, a copy of Town Meeting, and the pamphlet, "Oklahoma Story-1940."
  - Clippings, newsletter and the pamphlet, "The Enemy in Pasadena", 1950-1952; 9 items. (Box 89, Folder 8)
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1961-1969; 10 items. (Box 89, Folder 9)
    Includes a copy of The Current.
  - Clippings from assorted publications, 1970-1979; 22 items. (Box 89, Folder 10)
    Includes letters and a copy of The Washington Spectator.
  - Clippings from assorted newspapers, 1972-1979; ca. 50 items. (Box 89, Folder 11)
  - Clippings and photocopies from Pacific News Service, 1976-1980; 33 items. (Box 89, Folder 12)
    Includes 2 letters and press releases.
  - Clippings from assorted newspapers, 1980; 8 items. (Box 89, Folder 13)
- 9. Publicity and criticism, 1929-1980; 1.5 boxes
  This series contains assorted printed materials (such as clippings, leaflets, and press releases) that are about, or mention, McWilliams and/or his work. It also contains materials related to honors and recognitions he received, and, contrastingly, accusations of communist leanings or protests over his appearances. Other publicity and criticism materials may be found in the lecture files (Series 5), The Nation files (Series 7, box 88, folders 5 and 6), the Division of Immigration and Housing files (Series 3, folder 6), the monograph files (Subseries 6E), and the scrapbooks (Subseries 1D). Files are in chronological order, with undated materials at the beginning of the series.
  - Typed quotation, leaflets, and clippings, undated; 8 items. (Box 90, Folder 1)
  - Assorted publicity materials, 1929-1948; 22 items. (Box 90, Folder 2)
    Includes clippings, a personal memorandum, a leaflet, an invitation, and a typewritten manuscript of a review of Brothers Under the Skin. Also contains copies of The Chronicle, The Book Find News, and Fortnight.
  - Newspaper clippings, including reviews of Brothers Under the Skin, Prejudice, and A Mask for Privilege, 1931-1948; ca. 30 items. (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and printed materials re: protests over McWilliams's appearance in Portland, 1948-1950; ca. 50 items. (Box 90, Folder 4)
    Includes a copy of the Oregon Democrat, leaflets, and newspaper clippings.
  - Reviews of California: the Great Exception, 1949-1950; ca. 40 items. (Box 90, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1951; 6 items. (Box 90, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 2 conference registration forms and a program, 1952-1954; 7 items. (Box 90, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings on McWilliams's "leftist" or "communist" leanings, 1952-1954; ca. 50 items. (Box 90, Folder 8)
    Subjects include the Emergency Civil Liberties Committee.
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1957; 2 items. (Box 90, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings on protests to McWilliams's lecture appearances, 1960-1965; ca. 50 items. (Box 90, Folder 10)
    Includes a leaflet purporting McWilliams's communist ties.
  - Assorted publicity materials, 1963-1969; 19 items. (Box 90, Folder 11)
    Includes clippings, a press release, a newsletter, and reviews of North from Mexico.
  - Reviews of The California Revolution, 1968-1969; 35 items. (Box 90, Folder 12)
  - Assorted publicity materials, 1970-1975; 43 items. (Box 90, Folder 13)
    Assorted printed materials, including clippings, letters, promotional leaflets for his books, and the handbook of production information for the film Chinatown. Subjects include McWilliams's retirement from The Nation.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1970-1975; ca. 40 items. (Box 90, Folder 14)
    Subjects include McWilliams's retirement.
  - Publicity materials relating to the USC Honorary Degree, 1974; 50 items. (Box 91, Folder 1)
    Assorted printed materials relating to the University of Southern California Honorary Doctor of Laws Degree McWilliams received on June 8th, 1974. Includes correspondence, twenty-two 8 x 10 black and white photographs, six 3.5 x 5 color photographs, seven color slides, three black and white negatives, the commencement program, leaflets, and clippings.
  - Assorted publicity materials, 1976-1978; 34 items. (Box 91, Folder 2)